Finding Aid for Hubbell Family Papers, 1859-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hubbell Family Papers 1859-1983
Hubbell family.
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
85217 Aa 2; Ac
Benzonia and Ann Arbor, Michigan; papers of individual family members, detailing in part activities in the Philippines, 1907-1912. The collection also contains photographs and albums of images from the period when they lived in the Philippines.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Hubbell family papers was donated by Theodore H. Hubbell (donor no. 4509 ) in 1983-1984.
The collection is open to research.
Clarence Hubbell, civil engineer, was born in 1870 and grew up in Benzonia, Michigan. In 1893, he received a degree in civil engineering from the University of Michigan and subsequently worked for the Detroit Water Department. He married Winifred Temperance Waters, also of Benzonia, in 1895.
From 1907 to 1912 the Hubbell family lived in the Philippine Islands, where Clarence Hubbell worked as a water supply and public works engineer. Shortly after the family returned to Michigan, he established his own engineering firm in Detroit. He was a design and construction engineer for the Detroit Sewer System from 1916 to 1922 and served on the Detroit Rapid Transit Commission from 1925 to 1940. He retired in 1946. In 1950, Clarence Hubbell was killed in an automobile accident.
Clarence Hubbell's oldest son, Theodore, was born in 1897 in Detroit. He graduated from Benzonia Academy in 1915. An entomologist, Theodore Hubbell received his PhD in Zoology from the University of Michigan in 1934. He was on the University of Florida faculty from 1923 to 1946 and then came to the University of Michigan where he taught and was director of the Museum of Zoology. He retired in 1968.
The Hubbell Family Papers date from 1859 to 1983 and measure one linear foot. Included in the collection are genealogical material, and correspondence and other papers of individual family members.
Subjects:
Benzonia (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Detroit.; Women--Michigan--Benzonia.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Benzonia (Mich.); Benzonia Academy.; Beulah (Mich.); Children.; Crystal Lake (Mich.: Lake); Dwellings--Michigan--Milford.; Hubbell, Clarence, 1870-1950.; Hubbell, Winifred.; Milford (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Railroads--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Benzonia.; Waters family.
Contributors:
Hubbell, Clarence, 1870-1950.; Hubbell, Theodore Huntington, 1897-1989.; Hubbell, Winifred.; Waters, Martha.; Waters, Otis.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.
- Genealogical Material/Historical
  The genealogical material documents the Bliss, Case, Hubbell, Huntington and Waters families and includes a family tree, handwritten and printed genealogies and a chronology of family events.
  - Bliss Family (Box 1)
  - Case Family (Box 1)
  - Hubbell Family (Box 1)
  - Hubbell and Huntington Families (Folder 1)
  - Waters Family (Box 1)
  - Benzonia, Michigan file (Box 1)
- Family Members Papers
  The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence and other papers of individual family members, much of which details their activities in the Philippine Islands from 1907 to 1912. Winifred Hubbell, in particular, wrote detailed accounts of the family's journey to the Philippines and of their experiences there in letters to her mother, Martha Waters. In 1912 Winifred traveled to Germany with the children and wrote frequently to Clarence who remained in the Philippines. The following year the family returned to Michigan but Clarence had to return to the Philippines to finish his work. His letters to Winifred during this period reflect the changing attitudes of Filipinos towards Americans.
  Among the personal papers of Winifred and Clarence Hubbell, the researcher will find autobiographical material concerning, in part, their experiences while growing up in Benzonia, Michigan. The papers of Theodore Hubbell reflect his involvement in the bicentennial project on historic houses in Benzonia and a reunion of Benzonia Academy graduates.
  - Clarence Hubbell (husband of Winifred)
    - Correspondence To Winifred and Family 1902-1926 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Other Correspondence 1849-1949 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Personal Papers 1907-1950 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Winifred Hubbell (wife of Clarence)
    - Correspondence To Clarence 1895-1914 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence To Martha Waters (mother) 1907-1912, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Other Correspondence 1882-1957 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Autobiographical Essays 1890-1946 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Detroit Woman's Club undated (Box 1)
    - Philippine Islands Essays, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Travel mementos and Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Theodore Hubbell (son of Clarence Hubbell)
    - Correspondence 1902-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Personal Papers 1907-1976 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Grace Hubbell (wife of Theodore Hubbell)
    - Correspondence 1928, 1939, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Children of Clarence and Winifred Hubbell
    - Correspondence to Parents 1912-1945 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Martha Waters (mother of Winifred Hubbell)
    - Correspondence 1859-1926 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Autobiographical Essays 1925 (Box 2)
  - Otis Bird Waters (father of Winifred Hubbell)
    - Sermons, 1860-1886 (Box 2)
      and other pastoral records while in Benzonia
    - Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - William S. Hubbell (grandfather of Clarence Hubbell)
    - Patent for processing wood 1853 (Folder 1)
- Photographs
  This series consists of photos of family activities in the Philippines, 1907-1912, and photos and postcards collected there; family photos of Clarence Hubbell and Winifred Waters Hubbell; photos of Benzonia, Michigan, and Benzonia Academy, Beulah, Michigan, Crystal Lake, the Hubbell home in Milford, Michigan, and Wamplers Lake, Michigan; and photos of the Waters family.
  - Benzonia and Benzonia Academy (Box 2)
  - Crystal City (now Beulah), Michigan and Crystal Lake (Box 2)
    (includes railroad photograph)
  - Hubbell family photographs [non-Philippine] (Box 2)
  - Hubbell home, Milford, Michigan, built 1924 [Hillhollow] (Box 2)
  - Hubbell honeymoon trip, Wampler's Lake 1926 (Box 2)
    (negatives only)
  - Philippines
    - Architecture (Box 2)
    - Dumaguete
      - Residence 1923 (Box 2)
      - Silliman Institute (Box 2)
      - Silliman Institute, formal portraits of Mrs. George Rorick Clark (Box 2)
    - Hubbell family photographs 1908-1912 (Box 2)
    - Hubbell homes, including Villa Benzonia in Manila (Box 2)
    - George W. Hubbell monuments (Box 2)
    - Manila, including post cards (Box 2)
    - Mindanao and Jolo Islands, postcards (Box 2)
      (Includes Moro and Bagobo tribes)
    - Natives, includes tribes from Luzon and Boso-Boso. (Box 2)
    - Officials (Box 2)
    - Schools. (Box 2)
      (see also Dumaguete, Silliman Institute)
    - Views (Box 2)
    - Views, Post cards (Box 2)
    - Water reservoirs/waterfalls, bridges and roads (Box 2)
  - Travel (Box 2)
  - Waters, Otis Bird and Martha Ann Hasseltine Bliss Waters (Box 2)
  - Waters family (Box 2)
  - Albums: (Box 2)
  - "Hubbell Family Pictures," circa 1890-1935 (Box 3)
    (includes Benzonia Academy photos)
  - "Philippine Pictures 1908-1913 Clarence W. Hubbell and Winifred Waters Hubbell." (Box 3)